Wilson, Ernest Henry, 1876-1930. Papers of Ernest Henry Wilson, 1896-1952: Guide.
Papers of Ernest Henry Wilson, 1896-1952.
- W.I: Biographical Material
  - Subseries W.I:F: Family and Friends Documents
    - Box 1
      - Folder 21 Collins, Elizabeth M.
        - Social Security Death Index (copy). There is speculation the “Elizabeth Collins” listed on the index is “Aunt Betty.”
      - Folder 22 Slate, Muriel Wilson.
        - Obituary (copy).
        - Letter Dunham to Slate, confirming election as Fellow of the Royal Horticulture Society, 1932.
- W.II: First Expedition to China for Messrs. Veitch, June 1899-April 1902.
  - Box 4
    - Folder 1
      - Memorandum and agreement between James Veitch & Sons, Royal Exotic Nursery, Kings Road, Chelsea, and EHW concerning Wilson's first expedition to China for Messrs. Veitch (March 27, 1899). Two copies, one includes a sheet with "alterations."
    - Folder 2
      - Copy of a letter from Charles Sprague Sargent to Veitch with advice for EHW's first expedition, March 17, 1899.
    - Folder 3
      - Bound notebook. On spine: "Wilson. Numerical list of seeds collected 1899-1901.", Contents of notebook:; Arnold Arboretum Library accession number: 39648.; NOTE: See also Series W.III, Box 6, Folder 13 for "Wilson plants received (at the Arnold Arboretum) from Veitch, November 1907."
    - Folder 4
      - EHW's notebook: "Hosie's itinerary. Tatien-lu to Chentu..." (Notes from A. Hosie, "Three years in Western China," 1887?)
    - Folder 5
      - Notebook. Records kept at the Veitch nurseries, 1899-1905. "Numerical list of seeds numbers: 1-1907 collected by E.H. Wilson on his first and second expeditions to China for Messrs. Veitch & Sons, 1899-1905; records kept at the Veitch nurseries.", Contents of notebook:; The records include: Dates received - Number - Department or Foreman - Name - Remarks on seed package and in letters: - Habit, Height, Color, Soil, Elevation, Habitat, Results. A copy of a letter dated December 30, 1903, written by E.H. Wilson is glued to the notebook cover. NOTE: Arnold Arboretum Library accession number 39647.
- W.III: Second Expedition to China for Messrs. Veitch, 1903-1905.
  Diaries and Field Notes: Book I-Book IV (Wilson's numbers.) Folders 2-10.
  NOTE: Records kept by Messrs. Veitch on seed propagation results for seeds collected 1903-1905 are found in: Series W.II, Box 4, Folder 5, Section Two.
  - Box 5
    - Folder 1
      - General instructions from Messrs. Veitch, 1902.
    - Folder 2
      - Book I: April-June 16, 1903. Western Hupeh and Ichang to Kiating Fu: November 30, 1903-December 22, 1903. Kiating to Tung Sing: April 23-April 30, 1904. Sui Fu to mouth of Tung.
    - Folder 3
      - Book IA: April 25-June 18. Ichang to Kiating. Plant notes.
    - Folder 4
      - Book II, Part 1: June 25-July 26, 1903. Kiating Fu to Tachien-lu and return via Wa-chan.
    - Folder 5
      - Book II, Part 2: July 28-August 4, 1903. Kiating Fu to Tachien-lu and return. Turned around, this notebook has a separate section: July 14-23, 1903, Tachien-lu, Tung Valley.
    - Folder 6
      - Book IIA: June 25-August 4, 1903. Plant notes.
    - Folder 7
      - Book III, Part 1: August 10-September 23, 1903. Kiating Fu to Sung Pan Ting via Cheng Fu and return.
    - Folder 8
      - Book IV: October 13-23, 1903; November 6-20, 1903. Kiating to Mount Omei and return.
    - Folder 9
      - (Unnumbered Book): March 15-April 24, 1904. Ichang to Sui Fu.
    - Folder 10
      - (Unnumbered Book): May 6-September 19, 1904. Kiating to Chengtu. Includes hand-drawn map and insert of six leaves of geological notes.
  - Box 6
    - Folder 11
      - Notebook. "Field Notes." 1903-1905.
        Contents of notebook:
        NOTE: Arnold Arboretum Library accession number: 39649.
    - Folder 12
      - EHW's account notes with Messrs. Veitch, 1903-1904.
    - Folder 13
      - "Wilson plants received from Veitch, November 1907." List of plants collected by EHW for Messrs. Veitch and received at the Arnold Arboretum. 8 pages in a folder. Seed collection numbers: 1-1310 (see Series W.II, Box 4, Folder 3) with exception of 4c. Seed collection numbers: 1400-1900 (see Folder 11 of this Series, W.III.), NOTE: Arnold Arboretum Library accession number: 39922.
    - Folder 14
      - Five bank drafts "Hong Kong and Shanghai Banking Corp," 1903-1904.
- W.IV: Wilson's Third Expedition to China—The First for The Arnold Arboretum, 1907-1909., NOTE: Folders 7, 8, 9 contain notebooks with collection data from two expeditions to China for the Arnold Arboretum. (1907-1909 and 1910-1911)
  - Box 7
    - Folder 1
      - EHW's draft on financial terms for the 1907-1909 expedition, August 8, 1906. (1 page)
    - Folder 2
      - Agreement between Harvard College and EHW concerning the first expedition to China for the Arnold Arboretum. Signed December 6, 1906 by Charles Sprague Sargent and Wilson. (2 copies)
    - Folder 3
      - Diary from expedition in Western Hupeh, accompanied by Walter Reaves Zappey. Notes include weather observations, plant lists, notes on expenses. Turned around, this diary lists photographs taken, with data on dates, motives, and technicalities, April 2-19, 1907.
    - Folder 4
      - Diary from expedition to Western Szechuan, Min Valley, Mount Wa, Mont Omei, with Kiating as a base. Includes one map, May 11-August 12, 1908.
    - Folder 5
      - Diary. Western Szechuan with Kiating as a base, September 4-24, l908.
    - Folder 6
      - Diary. Western Hupeh with Ichang as a base. Beside botanical observations, this diary includes comments on photography and on hunting with Walter Reaves Zappey, May 3-June 10, 1909.
    - Folder 7
      - Field notes. Wilson used a new collection number sequence for the Arnold Arboretum., Contents of notebook:; This notebook also includes lists of "sample packages dispatched." Package numbers 2-320 (May 1907-February 1908). p. 271. Package numbers 1-327 (August 1908-February 22, 1909). pp. 271, 273.; NOTE: Arnold Arboretum Library accession number: 39526.
  - Box 8
    - Folder 8
      - Numerical list of specimens collected on EHW's Arnold Arboretum expeditions to Eastern Asia, "1907-1918," [sic] Vol. 1., Contents of notebook:; NOTE: Arnold Arboretum Library accession number: 39525.
    - Folder 9
      - Notes. Numerical list of seeds collected on EHW's Arnold Arboretum expeditions to Eastern Asia, 1907-1908, 1910, which were planted in the Arboretum nurseries., Contents of notebook:; NOTE: Arnold Arboretum Library accession number: 39611.
    - Folder 10
      - Account book., Contents of account book:
    - Folder 11
      - Account sheet. "The John E. Thayer Expedition to China, 1907-1909." Signed by EHW, December 12, 1909., NOTE: John E. Thayer Expedition refers to Museum of Comparative Zoology support of their staff member Walter Reaves Zappey on this expedition.
    - Folder 12
      - Account sheet. "The Arnold Arboretum Expedition to China, 1906-1909." Signed by EHW, December 12, 1909. Two similar sheets.
    - Folder 13
      - Account sheet. "E.H. Wilson in account with President and Fellows, Harvard College." "EHW Acct. July 15, 1907." Signed by EHW, Ichang, July 25, 1907. Four sheets.
    - Folder 14
      - A letter from Harvard College with information on a draft, sent on July 13, 1909.
- W.V: Wilson's Fourth Expedition to China—The Second for The Arnold Arboretum, 1910-1911., Notes on seeds and plants collected during this expedition are found in Series W.IV, Box 7, Folder 7. Collection numbers 4000-4462. Notes on specimen collected during this expedition are found in Series W.IV, Box 8, Folder 8. Collection numbers 4006-4766. Notes on seeds planted in the Arnold Arboretum from this expedition are found in Series W.IV, Box 8, Folder 9.
  - Box 9
    - Folder 1
      - Agreement between Harvard College and EHW concerning the second expedition to China for the Arnold Arboretum. Signed by Charles Sprague Sargent and Wilson, February 26, 1910.
    - Folder 2
      - Proposed circular to subscribers towards the Wilson Chinese Expedition, April 25, 1910.
    - Folder 3
      - List of British subscribers to the expedition by EHW to Western China, 1910.
    - Folder 4
      - Diary. Expedition to Sungpan. Notes from August 4, 1910 describe a visit to an experimental farm outside Chengtu, June 4-August 4, 1910.
    - Folder 5
      - Diary. Expedition with Chengtu as a base, August 8-September 3,1910.
    - Folder 6
      - Expense accounts. "The Arnold Arboretum's Second Expedition to China, 1910-1911. The President and Fellows of Harvard University in account with E.H. Wilson." pp. 2-24.
    - Folder 7
      - Two medical bills: one from Ichang, 1910, and one from the Friends Mission, Chentu, 1911.
- W.VI: The Fifth Expedition to Japan—February 1914-January 1915.
  - Box 10, NOTE: Folders 5, 6, 7, 8 all contain extensive notations made on loose leaves removed from a notebook (by Wilson?).
    - Folder 1
      - Field notes on collected plants and seeds. Collection numbers 6001-7199 (numbers 4744-6000 have not been used.) No notations are made in this note book between July 7 and September 23. Additional notes, on collections numbered 6469-6558 of Prunus, are found on pp. 106-112. Notes include plant names, dates and places. Primary notes are made in EHW's hand. February 18-October 24, 1914., NOTE: Arnold Arboretum Library Accession number 39527.
    - Folder 2
      - Field notes of collected plants and seeds. On spine: "Wilson numerical lists, Vol. III., Nos. 7200-7888. Collection numbers 7200-7888." July 19-December 4, 1914., NOTE: Even if the collection numbers follow the ones in the previous note book, the collection dates are not in sequence. Collection notes from September and October appear in both books of field notes.; NOTE: Arnold Arboretum Accession number 39528.
    - Folder 3
      - Notations on plants in alphabetical order. Place names are given. Dates and names of Japanese botanists appear occasionally.
    - Folder 4
      - Notations on plants in alphabetical order. Includes notes on Japanese botanists and references to earlier collectors; for example Charles Sprague Sargent. Place names are given, but seldom dates for observations. Some notes are made in a handwriting different than Wilson's.
    - Folder 5
      - Notes on plants and places in alphabetical order. Abies to Vitis, July-September 1914. (44 pages)
    - Folder 6
      - Notes from Mount Takai. (3 pages)
    - Folder 7
      - "Conifers of Formosa and Liukiu Islands in the Tokyo Botanical Herbarium examined with Dr. Hayata, Nov. 6, 1914." (22 pages)
    - Folder 8
      - Transcription of "Conifers of Formosa and Liukiu Islands in the Tokyo Botanical Herbarium examined with Dr. Hayata, Nov. 6, 1914." (22 pages)
    - Folder 9
      - "Corean conifers; material in Tokyo Botanical Garden Herbarium, examined with Dr. Nakai, November 7, 1914." (5 pages)
    - Folder 10
      - Account book. "E.H. Wilson in account with the Arnold Arboretum Journey to Japan, 1914." pp. 1-33. (pp. 41-148 of book used for accounts 1928-30.)
    - Folder 11
      - Transcription of account book from Folder 10.
  - Box 11
    - Folder 1
      - Transcribed field notes on collected plants and seeds 7200-7888, July 19-December 4, 1914. Corresponding box/folder numbering 10:2. From EHW's 5th Expedition—Japan, February 1914-January 1915.
    - Folder 2
      - Transcribed field notes on plants in alphabetical order, corresponding box/folder numbering 10:3-10:9. Place names are given. Spiral bound notebook. From EHW's 5th Expedition—Japan, February 1914-January 1915.
    - Folder 3
      - Transcribed field notes on collected plants and Seeds 6001-7199, February 18-October 26, 1914. Corresponding box/folder numbering 10:1. From EHW's 5th Expedition—Japan, February 1914-January 1915.
    - Folder 4
      - Transcribed field notes on collected plants and seeds 6001-7199, February 18-October 26, 1914. Corresponding box/folder numbering 10:1. From Wilson's 5th Expedition—Japan, February 1914-January 1915. Modern names for the Wilson accessions 6001-11, 268. (David Mitchner, Arboretum staff member 1984-1987)
    - Folder 5
      - Transcribed notes 10:3-10:9 on Wilson's 5th Expedition—Japan, February 1914-January 1915.
    - Folder 6
      - Transcribed notes, field data and diaries from two of EHW's six expeditions to the Far East. Transcribed October 1, 1985-September 30, 1986 by Carin Dohlman.
        Note in folder indicating that printout is a duplicate.
- Series W.VII: Wilson's Sixth Expedition to the Far East—Japan, Korea, Manchuria, Formosa, and Islands in the Japanese Sea, January 1917-March 1919.
  - Box 12, NOTE: Folders 7-18 contain loose-leaf notes made during 1917 and 1918, and "removed from diary" (by Wilson?). Also, a second set of folders 7-18 contain transcriptions of corresponding loose-leaf field notes.
    - Folder 1
      - Letter to Charles Sprague Sargent from F.R.S. Baulfour regarding "subscription" to Korea and Formosa expedition.
    - Folder 2
      - Collection notes. [February]-May 6, 1917. Collection numbers: 8000-8415. Okinawa, Liukiu Island, Bonin Island, Hachijo Island., Arnold Arboretum Library accession number: 39529.
    - Folder 3
      - Collection notes. May 17-December 9, [1917]. Collection numbers: 8216-9637. Korea and Manchuria: Islands of Dagelet, Island of Quelpaert., Arnold Arboretum Library accession number 39530.
    - Folder 4
      - Collection notes. [January]-June 12, 1918. Collection numbers: 9634-10375. Formosa via Japan, Kyushu Island, Mount Arisan, Mount Morrison., Arnold Arboretum Library accession number 39531.
    - Folder 5
      - Collection notes. June 17-September 17, 1918. Collection numbers: 10376-10756. Second trip to Korea, Korea to Formosa via Japan., Arnold Arboretum Library accession number 39532.
    - Folder 6
      - Collection notes. October 20, 1918-January 29, 1919. Collection numbers: 10757-11268. (on spine) Japan and Formosa., Arnold Arboretum Library accession number 39533.
    - Folder 7
      - "Karama Islands." March 2-6, 1917. (7 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
    - Folder 8
      - "Northern Korea." No date. (9 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
    - Folder 9
      - "Liukiu." February 25-March 1917. (5 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
    - Folder 10
      - "Diamond Mt." October 7-17, 1917. (5 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
    - Folder 11
      - "Idzu-Oshima?" (De Vriese Island.) No date. (6 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
    - Folder 12
      - "Quelpaert." "Saishu." No date. (3 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
    - Folder 13
      - "Kongo-san." [Korea] No date. (6 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
    - Folder 14
      - "Korean notes in alphabetical sequence removed from diary, Jan. 25, 1918. " A, B, C, Q, P, T only. (23 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
    - Folder 15
      - "Yalu Timber Co., Antung." No date. (2 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
    - Folder 16
      - "Varieties of Peonies, mountain cult. Yamamoto, near Osaka, May 8, 1918." (3 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
    - Folder 17
      - "Chosen, Karamatsu." No date. (6 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
    - Folder 18
      - "Formosa." No date. (16 pages)
      - Includes typed transcript. (draft)
      - A photocopy of a letter dated November 3, 1909 from Charles Sprague Sargent to Prof. Goodale, regarding Wilson photographs.
  - Box 13
    - Folder 1
      - Transcribed collection notes 8416-9202, May 17-December 9, 1917; 9:2. Wilson's 6th Expedition.
    - Folder 2
      - Transcribed collection notes 9203-9637, May 17-December 9, 1917; 9:2. Wilson's 6th Expedition.
    - Folder 3
      - Transcribed collection notes 10376-10756, June 17- September 17, 1918, 9:4. Wilson's 6th Expedition.
    - Folder 4
      - Transcribed collection notes 10757-11268, October 20-January 29, 1919, 9:5. Wilson's 6th Expedition.
    - Folder 5
      - Transcribed collection notes on habitat and plant descriptions. 9:6-9:17. Marked Duplicates. Wilson's 6th Expedition.
    - Folder 6
      - Transcribed collection notes 9:6-9:17 on habitat and plant descriptions. Wilson's 6th Expedition.
    - Folder 7
      - Transcribed collection notes 9634-10375, January-June 12, 1918; 9:3. Wilson's 6th Expedition.
    - Folder 8
      - Material on funding and contributors of the Wilson expedition for the Arnold Arboretum. Compiled by Sheila Connor, 1979.
    - Folder 9
      - EHW's itineraries for Japan trip (1914) and Korea (1917-1918) and copies of maps.
- Series W.VIII: Wilson's Visit to "Gardens of the World," October 1920-August 1922., NOTE: The collection notes in this series are not made in Wilson's handwriting.
  - Box 14
    - Folder 1
      - Catalog of the library of the Arnold Arboretum of Harvard University. Selected titles "prepared for Mr. E.H. Wilson to take along on his trip to visit gardens of the world." [Ethelyn Tucker, librarian, Arnold Arboretum, 1921]. Sections include Australia, New Zealand, India and Ceylon, Straits Settlements.
    - Folder 2
      - Alternating diary and collection notes. Australia. "Perth to Westonia." Collection numbers: 1-507. October 21, 1920-November 20, 1920.
    - Folder 3
      - Alternating diary and collection notes. Australia and New Zealand. "'Goolgardie to Widgremootha', Australian trip with Dr. D.A. Herbert", "Hills around Adelaide, S. A.," "New South Wales," "Sydney," "Trip to forest north of Sydney." Collection numbers: 520-717, October 21, 1920-January 9, 1921.
    - Folder 4
      - Diary notes. Australia and New Zealand. Notes are entered in ledger: "Australian 1921, Rough Diary," January 11, 1921-April 24, 1921.
    - Folder 5
      - Collection notes on loose leaves. Australia. Bribie Island, Fraser Island, Benarkin, Imbil. Collection numbers: 700-799, May 1921.
    - Folder 6
      - Diary notes. July 19, 1921-November 1, 1921. "India." Includes inserted loose leaf notes, October 21-November 1, 1921.
    - Folder 7
      - Notebook. England and France. Includes: "Linnean Herbarium," "Aldenham Honbi," "Brit. Museum," "Les Barres Arbor," "Edinburgh." Mainly notations on plants and locations with some comments. Includes personal names and addresses. Some shorthand notes. Some notes taken in unknown handwriting, May 31, 1922-July 17, 1922.
    - Folder 8
      - Notebook. England. Includes: "Wisley," "Hillier's nursery," "Kew," "Lilies in herbarium of Kew." Some notes are entered in the notebook turned around, July 21, 1922-August 11, 1922.
    - Folder 9
      - "Wilson's African plants." "Identified by R. Marloth, 4/25/23." Notes on one leaf. Collection numbers: 80-430.
    - Folder 10
      - Accounts. "Account Arnold Arboretum and Baring Bros. & Co., 1921-1922." (2 pages)
- W.IX: Expedition Photographs in Bound Volumes and Related Materials
  - Shelved volumes
    - Wilson, Ernest Henry. Vegetation of Western China: A series of 500 photographs with index and an introduction by Charles Sprague Sargent. London: Printed for the subscribers, 1912., An index issued to accompany a selection of 500 photographs from his Arnold Arboretum expedition to China, 1907-1909.
    - Wilson, Ernest Henry. Arnold Arboretum Expedition to China, 1907-1909: photographs. 1911., A set of 720 photographic glass plates of trees, forest views, landscapes, villages, and people, which were printed and bound in a six volume set in chronological order. Detailed documentation for each photograph is attached and includes locality, genus species plant name, description of site, tree height and dbh [diameter at breast height], altitude and date, or geographic location in the case of views.
    - Wilson, Ernest Henry. Arnold Arboretum Second Expedition to China, 1910-1911: photographs. 1911., A set of 374 glass plates of trees, forest views, landscapes, villages, and people, which were printed and bound in a three volume set in chronological order. Detailed documentation for each photograph is attached and includes locality, genus species plant name, description of site, tree height and dbh [diameter at breast height], altitude and date, or geographic location in the case of views.
    - Wilson, Ernest Henry. Arnold Arboretum Expedition to Japan, 1914: photographs. 1914., A set of 619 photographic glass plates of trees, forest views, landscapes, villages, and people, which were printed and bound in a six volume set in chronological order. Detailed documentation for each photograph is attached and includes locality, genus species plant name, description of site, tree height and dbh [diameter at breast height], altitude and date, or geographic location in the case of views.
  - Box 15
    - Folder 1: Photographs of Ernest Henry Wilson taken during Expeditions, Individual and Group
      - EHW's houseboat "Harvard" used in expedition to China, 1907-1908. Photograph taken in Ichang, China. (1 negative)
      - EHW with two other men in Ichang, China. (1 photograph)
      - EHW and Walter Reaves Zappey, who accompanied Wilson on trip, with dogs in China, 1908. (1 photograph)
      - EHW in Western China. (1 photograph)
      - EHW south of Ichang, January 20, 1909. (3 photographs)
      - EHW, Boy, Coolie, and Dog "Major" with 33 ordinary pheasants and 3 Reeves pheasants, February 1, 1909. (2 photographs)
      - EHW, Boy, and Coolie with 25 ordinary pheasants, 1909. (2 photographs)
      - Lilium, Ichang, China. "Packing Lily-bulbs", February 9, 1909. (2 photographs)
      - "My Chinese collectors, all faithful and true." Ichang, W. Hupeh. February 15, 1911.
      - EHW and the Japan Railway used on expedition in Japan. (2 different photographs)
      - EHW in nursery in Japan? (4 different images)
      - EHW in Japan. (2 different images)
      - EHW with a woman in Japan? (1 photograph)
      - EHW with his most efficient Japanese "Boy" Morita (second to right) at a Japanese fruit and vegetable market. (1 photograph)
      - EHW and J. Nakai in Oorigong, Japan. (1 photograph)
      - Ellen, Muriel, and Amah. Karasawa, Kyoto, Japan, 1913. (1 photograph)
      - Ellen Wilson and Muriel in tea ceremony in Tokyo, 1914. (1 photograph)
      - Ellen Wilson and Muriel in kimonos, Tokyo, 1914. (2 different photographs)
      - Muriel in front of a mirror wearing a kimono, Tokyo, 1914. (1 photograph)
      - EHW surrounded by Japanese officials from the forestry department, Korea, 1914. (1 photograph)
      - Diamond Mountains in Korea. "Entrance to fairyland." From 1917–1918 expedition. (1 photograph)
      - Diamond Mountains in Korea. "The worst is over." From 1917–1918 expedition. (1 photograph)
      - A young man with a girl. R. Kanakawa with Muriel? Chosen Hotel Seoul. (1 photograph)
      - Ellen Wilson, Muriel, and Payoda at the Xeyasu Shrine, May 13, 1914. (2 different photographs)
      - Ellen Wilson and Muriel seated at tables of the garden party at the British Consulate, Seoul, Korea. (1 photograph)
      - Ellen Wilson and Muriel in the group photograph of the garden party at the British Consulate, Seoul, Korea. (1 photograph)
      - EHW in Korea, 1917. (2 photographs)
      - Ellen Wilson with dog and Muriel and two unidentified men in the Diamond Mountains in Korea, 1917-1918. (1 photograph)
      - EHW, T. Miyoshi and H. Ushio taken in Kagoshima, presented to Wilson in 1917. (1 photograph)
      - EHW with reformed headhunters and armed policemen in the mountains of Formosa, 1918. (2 photographs)
      - EHW's collection of herbarium specimens made in Formosa and Korea during 1917 and 1918. Photographed in the atrium, 1st floor, Herbarium Wing, Hunnewell Building, April 1919. (1 photograph)
      - EHW and Formosan officials, no date. (1 photograph)
      - "Born Hunters." Two Formosans holding guns. (1 photograph)